Tuttle Family Papers, 1759-1953
Connecticut Historical Society
Tuttle Family Papers
1759-1953
Connecticut Historical Society, Hartford, Connecticut
Tuttle Family
0.5 linear feet (1 box)
Biographical Sketch
The Tuttle family lived primarily in North Haven and Hamden, Connecticut. Hezekiah Tuttle was born May 20, 1749 to Jude and Lydia (Atwater) Tuttle. He married Mary Turner on March 19, 1770. They had seven children: Jesse (3/8/1771-10/26/1847), Eli (3/1/1775-?), Elam (7/30/1777-10/11/1856), Caleb Atwater (11/18/1779-8/25/1844), Lydia (3/4/1783-?), Asahel (8/27/1787-3/16/1854), and Miles (9/3/1792-8/21/1836). Hezekiah Tuttle died January 5, 1829 at age 73.
Hezekiah’s oldest son, Jesse Tuttle, was born on March 8, 1771. Jesse Tuttle was baptized on May 28, 1780, according to the Congregational Society of North Haven. He married Esther Pierpont (10/27/1771-11/11/1857) on September 30, 1795. Esther was the daughter of Giles and Elizabeth (Cooper) Pierpont of North Haven, CT. Jesse and Esther had two sons, Dennis (3/31/1797-9/26/1878) and Zerah Pierpont (10/2/1800-?), and a daughter, Elizabeth (4/5/1809-11/13/1849). According to the accession records for this collection, Jesse Tuttle was a joiner and cabinetmaker in North Haven, CT. He died on October 26, 1847 at age 76.
Dennis Tuttle, Jesse’s oldest son, was born March 31, 1797. His first wife was Nancy T. Sanford, whom he married on September 24, 1820. Three years later, on December 15, 1823, Dennis Tuttle married Jerusha Gillet. According to the 1850 and 1870 US Federal Census records, he was a farmer in North Haven, CT and had at least one child, Lewis G. Tuttle, who was born around 1837.
Lewis Tuttle, a farmer in North Haven like his father, married a woman named Louisa around 1858 and their first child, Elizabeth, was born circa 1859. The 1870 US Federal Census lists Lewis and Louisa living with his father, Dennis, and their eleven-year-old daughter, Elizabeth and eight-year-old son, George. According to the 1880 US Federal Census, Lewis and Louisa had seven children in 1880: Libby (age 21 in 1880), George (age 19 in 1880), Martin (age 14 in 1880), Dennis (age 9 in 1880), Essie [Esther] (age 6 in 1880), and Willard (age 3 in 1880). In the 1920 US Federal Census, Lewis Tuttle, then age 84, is listed as living with his daughter, Elizabeth, then age 60, as well as his daughter, Esther Kinsey, then age 45, and his son-in-law, Ingham Kinsey, then age 50. It is presumed that this Esther Kinsey is the same woman whose documents appear in the Tuttle Family collection and whose letters refer to the Tuttle family.
For additional information about the Tuttle family, see Families of Ancient New Haven, compiled by Donald Lines Jacobus (Baltimore: Genealogical Publishing Co., Inc.: 1981).
Scope and Content
This collection, which encompasses the accession numbers 81604, 81605, and 81606, contains materials dated from 1759 to 1953, but the bulk of the collection was created between 1770 and 1850. It has been arranged according to the individuals who produced the records and, to the extent possible, proceeds chronologically with more general records in the later folders.
The majority of the collection consists of deeds. There are almost 70 separate deeds produced by or for Hezekiah Tuttle between 1770 and 1831. Jesse Tuttle and his son Dennis also have a number of deeds. The oldest document in this collection is a deed belonging to Simon Tuttle, a relative of Hezekiah and Jesse. Some of these deeds relate to North Haven residents, but do not, upon first glance, appear to belong directly to the Tuttle family. These deeds have been placed in a separate folder marked “North Haven Deeds” for the sake of clarity.
Another highlight of this collection is Jesse Tuttle’s account books that cover a thirty-six year period from 1792 to 1828. These accounts detail his working pattern including where he worked and how long for different people, including family members. Money that is owed to him or paid to him is also recorded in these logs.
This collection also contains the estate papers for three generations of Tuttle men: Jude, Hezekiah, and Jesse. These papers include inventories of their estates and to whom belongings, land, and money were left. In the case of Jesse Tuttle, the record from the Probate Court naming Dennis and Zerah Tuttle as administers of his estate.
During his lifetime, Jesse Tuttle was appointed a collector of the “Ecclesiastical Society Rates” in North Haven in 1798. Related to this appointment are the property lists from the residents of North Haven. These property lists acted as declarations of taxable property and the amount each individual owed seems to have been determined from their lists. The majority of the lists were from the years 1801 and 1802, which suggests that Jesse Tuttle may have been a collector for more than one year.
Finally, in this collection, there are a few documents that belonged to Esther Kinsey, the granddaughter of Dennis Tuttle. The church program from the dedication of the fifth meeting-house of the North Haven Congregational Church is of note along with an “In Memoriam” booklet featuring the poetry of the late Angelina M. Tuttle. Also among Esther Kinsey’s items is a birthday card from Mrs. Lydia C. Bowen of Arlington, California that mentions the Tuttle family, in particular Esther’s brother, George.
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions on access to the collection.
Accruals
The collection is closed.
Subject Headings
Personal Names
Tuttle, Hezekiah, 1749-1829.; Tuttle, Jesse, 1771-1847.
Subjects
Cabinetmakers --Connecticut --North Haven.; Decedents’ estates --Connecticut --North Haven.; Deeds --Connecticut --North Haven.; Taxation --Connecticut --North Haven.; Account books --1792-1828.; Account books --Connecticut --North Haven.
Contents:
- Papers
  - Simon Tuttle, Deed, 1759 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Jude Tuttle, Estate Papers, 1763 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Hezekiah Tuttle Papers, 1795-1826, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Hezekiah Tuttle, Deeds, 1770-1831 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Hezekiah Tuttle, Estate Papers, 1835 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Jesse Tuttle, Papers, 1833-1845 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Jesse Tuttle, Account Books, 1792-1815; 1816-1828 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Jesse Tuttle, Deeds, 1796-1847 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Jesse Tuttle, Declarations of Taxable Property from North Haven Residents, 1799-1802, 1814-1839 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Jesse Tuttle, Probate and Estate Papers, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Dennis Tuttle, Deeds, 1830-1861 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Tuttle Family Assorted Papers, 1820, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Kinsey, Esther Tuttle Papers, 1944, 1953, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - North Haven Deeds, 1765, 1773-1774, 1802 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Tuttle Family Genealogy Notes (Box 1, Folder 15)